Guide to the Robert Levy Family papers, 1929-1993 MS 831
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Robert Levy Family Papers
1929-1993
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Levy, Robert
MS 831
1 Linear Feet 1 Box
As part of the Los Angeles Jewish community, Robert Levy interacts with a number of its organizations and institutions. Mostly dated in the early 1930s, Robert Levy's family papers offer a glimpse of Jewish life in Los Angeles nearly a century ago.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Levy completed a Ph.D. in history at the University of California, Los Angeles, in 1998, and is well-known for his book "Ana Pauker: The Rise and Fall of a Jewish Communist." A staunch member of Temple B'nai Israel, Levy served on the Board of Trustees in 2019.
Founded in 1858, Congregation B'nai Israel is one of the oldest members of the Union for Reform Judaism (URJ), an organization that provides vision, direction and leadership to Reform Jews and congregations on spiritual, ethical, social justice and management issues. Its current synagogue has housed the congregation since 1954.
Scope and Contents
The Robert Levy family papers contain five Purple Quill Publications, documents such as programs, church bulletins, letters, certificates, and invitations, as well as several early editions of the B'nai B'rith Hillel Scribe, a publication no longer in print. Though the materials range in date from 1929 to 1993, the majority of the papers are from earlier dates. Because of their age, some of the materials are delicate and worn, the most vulnerable of which have been placed in mylar sleeves for protection from deterioration. This collection would be useful for researchers interested in the Houston Jewish community, early publications, or the Temple B'nai Israel. The collection does not contain many personal documents relevant to the Levy family, aside from one personal letter.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Robert Levy donated the materials in January of 2019.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in three series, as follows:
Series I: The Purple Quill Publications
Series II: Documents
Series III: Newsclippings: B'nai B'rith Hillel Scribe
The second series contains two sub-groups (Programs and Bulletins), and all materials are further sorted by date.
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
publications; documents; programs (documents); letters (correspondence); church bulletins; certificates; invitations; newspapers
Subjects (Persons)
Levy, Robert
- Series I: The Purple Quill Publications, 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Purple Quill: Commencement Issue, Volume VI, Number 5, 1929-06
  - The Purple Quill: Commencement Issue, Volume VII, Number 8, 1930-06
  - The Purple Quill: Volume VIII, Number 4, 1931-02
  - The Purple Quill: Volume VIII, Number 8 (2 copies)
- Series II: Documents, 1929-1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sub-Group A: Programs, 1929-1952
    - "Closing Exercises given by Miss Vida Godwin and Dancing Class" Program, 1929-05-17
    - Confirmation Services program from Congregation B'nai Israel, Galveston, Texas, 1929-06-14
    - Dr. Henry Cohen Memorial Sabbath Program at Temple B'nai Israel, Galveston Texas, 1952-06-12
  - Letter from Dr. Henry Barnston to Miss Audrey Levy, 1929-06-05
  - Ball High School Commencement Exercises Invitation, 1931-06-08
  - Sub-Goup B: Bulletins, 1956
    - Bulletin: Temple B'nai Israel, 1956-04-01
    - Bulletin: Temple B'nai Israel, 1956-04-15
    - Bulletin: Temple B'nai Israel, 1956-05-01
  - The Texas Jewish Historical Society Certificate honoring Mr. and Mrs. Herbert Given, 1993-03-12-1993-03-14
- Series III: Newsclippings: B'nai B'rith Hillel Scribe, 1932-1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - B'nai B'rith Hillel Scribe, Volume IV, Number 8, 1932-05
  - B'nai B'rith Hillel Scribe, Volume V, Number 1, 1932-10
  - B'nai B'rith Hillel Scribe, Volume VI, Number 6, 1934-04
  - B'nai B'rith Hillel Scribe, Volume VII, Number 1, 1934-10